Finding Aid for Ed Saunders papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ed Saunders papers 1983-1997
Saunders, Ed.
1 oversize folders
1.5 linear foot
2014140 Aa 2
Ed Saunders served the University of Michigan in many capacities, including as Director of the Microcomputer Education Center (1985-1986) and Director of the Information Technology Division's Office of Instructional Technology (1990-1997). Papers include department materials, department publications, and correspondence regarding the development of instructional technology use at the University of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Ed Saunders (donor no. 10924 ) in September 2012.
The collection is open to research.
Ed Saunders joined the University of Michigan's School of Education in 1981 after serving several years in Wyoming (Mich.) and Grand Rapids (Mich.) public schools.1 He served as a Senior Instructional Associate and Media Consultant at the School of Education's Instructional Strategy Services (1981-1984) and as the Dean's Assistant for Technology (1984-1985). He was later appointed Director of the Microcomputer Education Center (1985-1986), Associate Director of the Computing Center for User Services (1986-1990), and as the Director of the Information Technology Division's Office of Instructional Technology (1990-1997).2 Since 1997 he has served as Deputy Director of the University of Michigan Center for Health Communications Research (CHCR), however these years are not represented in the collection.
Sources:
Arabic Bilingual-Instructional Technology Grant, 1986-1984, box 1, folder 1, Ed Saunders, records, Bentley Historical Library.
Saunders, Ed, e-mail message to Nancy Deromedi, July 31, 2012.
"Edward W. Saunders," University of Michigan Center for Health Communications Research, accessed September 30, 2014, http://chcr.umich.edu/person.php?id=474.
The collection consists of three series representing Saunders' collection of department materials: School of Education, Computing Center, and Information Technology Division.
This collection follows Ed Saunders' career at the University of Michigan and includes Saunders' collection of department materials and correspondence. His collections primarily focus on University of Michigan projects aimed at promoting interactive learning with technology.
Subjects:
Information technology.; Saunders, Ed.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.; University of Michigan. Office of Instructional Technology.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan--Staff.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. School of Education.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- School of Education
  The School of Education series, 1986-1984 (0.3 linear feet) consists of a grant proposal and two videocassettes. The grant funded instructional technology use in Arabic-English bilingual education at University of Michigan and includes contextual information about Arabic speaking immigrant communities and available social services in Michigan. The two U-matic videocassettes contain several films by Clark Trow. The first videocassette includes the films "Denmark and its folk Schools", "German Schools and German Youth," "Leningrad and Moscow," and "Handicapped Children and Clinical Types." The second videocassette includes "School of Education Personnel and Activities," "American Experimental Schools," and "American and European Psychologists."
  - Arabic Bilingual-Instructional Technology Grant 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Clark Trow films undated, 2 U-matic videocassettes (Box 1)
- Computing Center
  The Computing Center series, 1985-1988 (0.5 linear feet) includes committee records, program records, and several reports. Researchers should note that this series contains University of Michigan's submissions to Apple's Design of the Personal Computer of the Year 2000 competition, where cross-discipline student teams submitted proposals for futuristic personal computer designs. This series also documents the user services support report, a multi-year effort in both the Computing Center and Information Technology Division evaluating user relations on campus.
  - Committee A April 29, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Computing Resources--Past and Present February 27, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Consultants exams undated (Box 1)
  - CRC pep rally October 20, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Design of the Personal Computer of the Year 2000, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Program Statement for the Microcomputer 1986 (Box 1)
  - Report to the Computing Policy Committee May 12, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Support report 1985-1988
    - Computing Center organization 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Information Technology Division (ITD) user services project 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Support for Information Technology 1988 (Box 1)
    - User Services Planning Team report 1986 (Box 1)
  - User services, 611 Church 1987 (Box 1)
- Information Technology Division
  The Information Technology Division series, 1988-1997 (0.8 linear feet plus one outsize folder) documents both U-M's Information Technology Division and its Office of Instructional Technology. This series includes correspondence, proposals, publications, and other associated materials. Included are planning and evaluation documents for Educom '89, a large instructional technology conference held at the University of Michigan. Also included are materials related to VIDS (Video Interactive Distribution System), a project by the Office of Instructional Technology to install an interactive multimedia network on campus.
  - Brochures 1995-1998 (Box 1)
  - Educom '89 1988-1989
    - Program and evaluation 1989 (Box 1)
    - Proposals 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Video Planning Committee 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Focus on Teaching flyers 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1989-1997 (Box 1)
  - New Media Center 1993-1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Office of Instructional Technology 1990-1997
    - Guidelines 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1990-1997 (Box 2)
    - Multimedia White Paper project 1990 (Box 2)
    - Operationalizing Information Technology services July 1994 (Box 2)
    - Project management retreat July 25, 1995 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan evaluation guidelines for instructional technology projects February 1995 (Box 2)
  - Oversize posters 1988-1995 (Folder 1)
  - VIDS (Video Interactive Distribution System) 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Apple-ATG December 1991-May 1992 (Box 2)
    - Proposal July 1990-June 1991 (Box 2)
Related Materials
The Bentley Historical Library has several related collections, including:
School of Education (University of Michigan) records
Computing Center (University of Michigan) records
Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records